{"tossups": [{"question": "During the first of these wars, the loser rejected a peace treaty offered by the victors after the Battle of Adys. The last of these wars began after Numidian raids on the losing side\u2019s territory. The victors of these wars developed a boarding device called a<em> corvus</em>, allowing them to use their superior legionaries in naval combat. Cato the Elder called for the third of these conflicts by repeatedly demanding that an enemy city must be destroyed. For the point, name this series of ancient wars for control of the Mediterranean between Rome and Carthage.", "answer": "<b> Punic</b> Wars (prompt on descriptions of \u201cwars between Rome and Carthage,\u201d or partial descriptions thereof, before \u201cRome\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "People of this nationality were expelled from Bisbee by the Phelps Dodge mining company. A racial slur for people originally from this country names a 1954 US operation that monitored these people, who were issued seasonal work passes in the Bracero Program. These people were the primary targets of violence during the Zoot Suit Riots in Los Angeles. For the point, identify these people who, after land reforms by Porfirio Diaz, began migrating north to the US.", "answer": "<b> Mexican</b> Americans (accept<b> Mexico</b> and other word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man inserted a bacchanale into the \u201cParis version\u201d of an opera inspired by the Wartburg Song Contest. While exiled to Switzerland for his role in Dresden\u2019s May Uprising, he wrote the essay<em> Artwork</em> <em>of the Future</em>, laying out his idea of the \u201ctotal work of art,\u201d or<em> Gesamtkunstwerk</em>. The patronage of King Ludwig II allowed this composer of<em> Tannh\u00a8auser</em> to construct a theater for his \u201cmusic dramas\u201d at Bayreuth. For the point, name this German opera composer of the<em> Ring Cycle</em>.", "answer": "Richard<b> Wagner</b> ([ree-kard vahg-ner], but be lenient) Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A genre of still lifes featuring books produced in this region is called<em> chaekgeori</em>. Intricate gold and jade crowns modeled after trees were worn by early rulers of this region\u2019s Silla kingdom. This region was one of the leading producers of green-glazed celadon during the Goryeo dynasty. A later king of this region\u2019s Choson dynasty is credited with inventing its modern alphabet,<em> hangul</em>. For the point, name this peninsula, ruled in the 15th century by King Sejong.", "answer": "<b> Korea</b>n Peninsula (accept North and/or South<b> Korea</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler was imprisoned in the castle of Ham after a failed coup. This ruler fought alongside Victor Emmanuel at the Battle of Solferino, liberating Lombardy from Austria. A decade later, this man was provoked by the Ems Dispatch into declaring war against Otto von Bismarck\u2019s country; that war ended poorly for this man, who was captured at the Battle of Sedan in 1871. For the point, name this loser of the Franco-Prussian War, a Second Empire ruler of France and nephew of France\u2019s first Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon III</b> (accept<b> Louis-Napoleon</b> Bonaparte; do not prompt on Napoleon alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s resistance movement was targeted in Operation Verano, an attempt to flush him out of the Sierra Maestra region, where he had established a base after landing on the ship<em> Granma</em>. This man led an unsuccessful attack on the government\u2019s Moncada Barracks, but his later July 26 movement seized control of the country away from Fulgencio Batista in 1959. For the point, name this communist Cuban strongman who died in 2016.", "answer": "Fidel<b> Castro</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Early studies of these events were performed by Fritz Zwicky and Walter Baade, who coined their name. The accelerated expansion of the Universe was first noted via the observation that some of these events were dimmer than expected. The brightest observed celestial event in history was one of these events that occurred in 1006 AD, while another of these events in 1054 AD was recorded by Chinese astronomers and led to the creation of the Crab nebula. For the point, name these events in which stars violently explode.", "answer": "<b> supernova</b> (do not accept or prompt on nova)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This dynasty came to power after defeating Xiang [shee-ang] Yu at the Battle of Gaixia [gai-shee-ah] in a contention against the rival Chu. Wang Mang attempted to usurp this dynasty by establishing the Xin [shin] line. The<em> Record of the Grand Historian</em> was compiled by Sima Qian [chee-ahn] during this dynasty, whose other achievements include establishing the Silk Road. For the point, name this dynasty that shares its name with China\u2019s majority ethnic group and succeeded the Qin [chin].", "answer": "<b> Han</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One ruler from this region allied with the exiled Tostig Godwinson, but was defeated at the Battle of Fulford. This region was the source of the Great Heathen Army, which conquered much of England before their defeat at Edington by Alfred the Great. Rulers born in region included Canute the Great and Harald Hardrada, and men from this region sacked Lindisfarne in 793 AD. For the point, name this region, the home of Viking invaders.", "answer": "<b> Scandinavia</b> (accept<b> Norway</b>; accept<b> Denmark</b> and/or<b> Sweden</b> after \u201cGreat Heathen Army\u201d is mentioned; prompt on Northern Europe) Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This structure was built after Joseph Darst accepted the Levee Tunnel plan to move nearby railways. After a group known as \u201cJennie May\u201d planned this structure as part of a riverfront revitalization project, FDR authorized it in 1935 as the US\u2019 first National Historic Site. Eero Saarinen designed this centerpiece of the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial to honor Lewis and Clark. For the point, name this curved monument on the Mississippi River near St. Louis.", "answer": "<b> Gateway Arch</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> St. Louis Arch</b>; prompt on the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s regime, Ta Mok, known as \u201cBrother Number Five,\u201d carried out many massacres. A place known as the \u201cHill of the Poisonous Trees,\u201d or Tuol Sleng, was used as an execution center in this man\u2019s regime under Comrade Duch [dook]. This man\u2019s regime replaced a general who deposed Norodom Sihanouk, Lon Nol. From Year Zero onward, this man attacked the \u201cNew People\u201d who lived in urban areas and executed them in the \u201ckilling fields.\u201d The Khmer Rouge was led by, for the point, what genocidal Cambodian dictator?", "answer": "<b> Pol Pot</b> (accept<b> Saloth Sar</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Thomas Ruffin Grey recorded a series of conversations with this man shortly before this man died, producing a book that lent its name to a William Styron novel. This man related his frequent visions in his Baptist sermons and started his most notable action upon seeing a solar eclipse. This man was hanged along with several of his followers after he led the killing of sixty white people in Southampton County, Virginia. For the point, name this leader of an 1831 slave uprising, the deadliest in American history.", "answer": "Nat<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A girl and a boy in this book discuss the sex of a cat, then realize that neither of them knows the name of a male\u2019s genitalia. This book ends abruptly after a character declares \u201cif only there were no other people in the world.\u201d The main character of this book shares a brief kiss with Peter van Daan and writes entries into a journal that she dubs \u201cKitty.\u201d For the point, name this book that describes a Jewish girl\u2019s experience hiding from the Nazis in Amsterdam.", "answer": "The<b> Diary of Anne Frank</b> (accept The<b> Diary of a Young Girl</b>; accept anything mentioning", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "One ruler of this name may have come to power by defeating a sorcerous usurper named Gaumata; that man recorded his empire\u2019s history in the Behistun Inscription. Another king of this name was left to die by the Bactrian satrap Bessus and fled from the Battle of Gaugamela in his chariot; that last ruler of this name was dethroned by Alexander the Great. A \u201cGreat\u201d ruler of this name launched a failed invasion of Greece in 490 BC. For the point, give this name shared by three Persian rulers, the first of whom lost at Marathon.", "answer": "<b> Darius</b> (accept<b> Darius</b> I or<b> Darius</b> the Great; accept<b> Darius</b> III)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Four years after this company was purchased for $4 billion by the Brazilian-backed firm 3G Capital in the largest leveraged buyout in its industry\u2019s history, this company \u201cpurchased\u201d Tim Hortons in a tax inversion scheme that put its headquarters in Ontario. The predecessor of this company was prefixed with the word \u201cInsta-\u201d, in honor of the Insta-machines it was inspired to use by McDonald\u2019s. The \u201cimagery of something big\u201d inspired the signature item of, for the point, what fast food chain that sells the Whopper?", "answer": "<b> Burger King</b> (accept<b> Insta-Burger King</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Shortly before his death, this man acted as a guide and navigator for an expedition to Nantucket Sound aboard the<em> Swan</em>. This man harvested fish from the muddy banks of the Eel River and explained methods of fertilizing corn and beans according to an account by William Bradford. For the point, name this Patuxet Native American who lived among the Plymouth colonists and whose agricultural prowess provided food for the first Thanksgiving.", "answer": "<b> Squanto</b> (or<b> Tisquantum</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event had a much higher survival rate than the similar loss of the<em> USS Akron</em> four years earlier. A. A. Hoehling sued Universal Studios over plagiarizing his claim that this event was caused by sabotage. Herbert Morrison recorded live coverage of this event to be played alongside newsreel footage. In response to this event, the<em> Graf Zeppelin II</em> used helium to achieve its buoyancy instead of hydrogen. For the point, name this 1937 disaster in which thirty-six people died when an airship burst into flame.", "answer": "LZ 129<b> Hindenburg</b> disaster (accept equivalents like<b> Hindenburg</b> fire, crash, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A park in this city contains \u201cla torre Rosa,\u201d the home of an architect who designed a multicolored mosaic salamander known as \u201cthe dragon.\u201d In this city, the Nativity, Passion, and Glory Fa\u00b8cades adorn a Gothic and Art Nouveau-styled cathedral that was left unfinished by its architect, Antoni Gaudi. The Sagrada Familia is located in, for the point, what city that hosted the 1992 Summer Olympics and is the capital of Catalonia in Spain?", "answer": "<b> Barcelona</b> Page 5", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "Joseph Rakes used one of these objects to attack civil rights activist Ted Landsmark, as shown in a 1976 photograph taken in Boston. The Supreme Court cases of<em> Eichman v. U.S.</em> and<em> Texas v. Johnson</em> dealt with the desecration of these objects, which is currently a protected form of free speech. Betsy Ross supposedly convinced George Washington that these objects should have five-pointed, not six-pointed stars. For the point, name this American symbol whose stripes represent the 13 colonies.", "answer": "American<b> flag</b>s (accept colloquial names, like<b> Old Glory</b> or the<b> Star Spangled Banner</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One week after this man\u2019s death, Alexander Graf von Hoyos received a metaphorical \u201cblank check\u201dfor war. This man was the presumptive heir to Franz Joseph, his uncle, who was the second-to-last Habsburg to rule in Europe. The Black Hand orchestrated this man\u2019s death in Sarajevo. Gavrilo Princip assassinated, for the point, what archduke whose 1914 death led to an invasion of Serbia and the First World War?", "answer": "Archduke<b> Franz Ferdinand</b> of Austria <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A league of cities on this peninsula met at the Fanum Voltumnae and included Velzna. Another alliance based on this peninsula included cities like Cora, Tusculum, and Alba Longa and signed the Treaty of Cassius with a nearby empire in 493 BC. The southern part of this peninsula was once known as Magna Graecia for its Greek colonies and was defended by Pyrrhus of Epirus. For the point, name this peninsula home to the Etruscans and other peoples conquered by the early Romans.", "answer": "<b> Italia</b>n peninsula (accept<b> Italy</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}